Finding Aid for the Michael and Susan Kahn Collection of Political Cartoons LSC.2419
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 1. American Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, 1798-2020; Series 1; 24.2 linear feet (14 boxes, 1 map folder)
  - Splitting the Party (The Entering Wedge), 1872; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
    Currier & Ives produced many of the important decorative prints of 19th century America. Their hand- colored lithographs covered a wide range of every phase of mid-century life and history, form city and country views, family life, portraits, comic prints, sports, etc., to political cartoons and newsworthy illustrations. These pictures were made by most of the celebrated artists of the time such as Thomas Nast, Otto Knirsch, Thomas Worth, as well as many others. Immensely popular and cheap, these prints were widely distributed but often mishandled and few survive today. Prints marked "N. Currier, N.Y." date from 1835 when Nathaniel Currier opened his lithographic shop until 1857 when James Ives became his partner and the firm's prints were marked "Published by Currier & Ives" from then on until the firm was liquidated in 1907. During that time the firm was carried on by the sons of the founders and flourished until the advent of chromolithography and photo-engraving in addition to the growing popularity of the illustrated newspaper caused their manual method of printing to become obsolete and unfashionable. (Source: Seller's note, see file)
  - The Constitution and Its Nurses, circa 1844; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The Great Exhibition of 1860, 1 Lithograph. Some foxing. (Box 86, Folder 4)
    Probably drawn by Louis Maurer. Source: LOC catalog
  - The Impending Crisis, Or, Caught in the Act, 1860; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
    Probably drawn by Louis Maurer. Source: UCLA catalog
  - The Last-Ditch of the Chivalry, or a President in Petticoats, 1865; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The People's Pocket Piece Discharged, 1841; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The Political "Siamese" Twins (The Offspring of Chicago Miscegenation), 1864; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The Radical Party on a Heavy Grade, 1868; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The Smelling Committee, 1868; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - The True Peace Commissioners, 1864; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Triumph of Principle or How to Preserve the Purity of Elections, circa 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - An Angry Snarl Between Friendly Relations, circa 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - British Whig Trap to Catch Voters, circa 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Cutting Down the Hickory Tree and Disturbing the Crow's Nest, 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - General Grant "Fighting It Out On A New Line.", circa 1868; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Matty's Perilous Situation Up Salt River, 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
    "Salt River" was a colloquial term for political misfortune or failure SOURCE: LOC
  - Notice to Quit. March 4th 1841, 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - The Great Match at Baltimore. Between the "Illinois" Bantam "And the Old Cock" of the White House., 1860; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - The Illustrious Footsteps, circa 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - The Irrepressible Conflict, 1860; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
    Note culturally sensitive language.
  - The Salt River Invincibles, circa 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Winter Amusement 1841 Going Down Hill (Kicked Out), circa 1841; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - House Intelligence Committee Russian Report, Dep. Attorney General Rosenstein Articles of Impeachment, 2018 May 1; 1 Drawing (Box 86, Folder 6)
    Telnaes' cartoon refers to the Mueller Report, officially titled the Report on the Investigation into Russian Interference in the 2016 Presidential Election. The investigation was initiated in 2017 and published in 2019.
    Original editorial cartoon artwork by Ann Telnaes published in the Washington Post on May 1, 2018. Appears to be pencil (mostly erased), with black ink pen and water color or acrylic paint (only shades of red, black and gray are used). Work is inscribed, "To Michael and Susan with Warm Regards (no flames though...). Ann Telnaes 5/1/2018
  - Trouble in the Spartan Ranks, 1843; 1 Lithograph. Per purchase note: This copy is poor, with toning, light staining to bottom portion, lots of small tears, anda large chunk missing from the upper left corner, not affecting any of the action or text of the cartoon. (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Rollin Kirby's "Tammany", 1928 September 24; 1 Drawing. Original pen and ink drawing on paper showing white paint to cover mistakes before publication. Paper is missing small portion of upper left corner and larger portion of upper right corner (dollar sign). Small portion of upper right corner is separated and included in this folder. (Box 86, Folder 7)
    Rollin Kirby's "Tammany" drawing was the 1929 Pulitzer Prize Winner for Editorial Cartooning. See Pulitzer web page: https://www.pulitzer.org/winners/rollin-kirby-1
    Inscribed to Ralph Pulitzer, who was publisher of the New York World newspaper in 1929.
  - The Soviet delegate (Vishinisky) unpacks his briefcase., 1952 November 30; 1 Print (Box 86, Folder 7)
  - A Convention of Secessionists After the War [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/4 x 5 1/2 (Box 95, Folder 1)
    Civil War patriotic envelopes were popular between 1861 and 1865. They were produced by and sold to those in the Union and the Confederacy. SOURCE: University of Texas at San Antonio blog post (2011): https://www.utsa.edu/ovations/vol6/story/envelopes.html
  - A.L. J.D. His Marque [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/8 x 5 1/2" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Alfred E. Smith, National Portrait Gallery [postcard], 1998; 1 Postcard. Measures approximately 4 x 6". Postcard is unused and not postmarked or stamped. (Box 95, Folder 1)
    Postcard featuring art work created in 1934 by Paolo Garretto of former governor of New York Al Smith. Smith is standing tall amongst New York City high rises holding his arms out and smiling. A steam ship passes by on the river in the foreground. He is wearing a bow tie and holds a hat in one hand; he has a heart-shaped decoration on his chest with an American flag design.
  - Championship Prize - Lincoln and Davis in Five Rounds [Abraham Lincoln and Jefferson Davis envelopes], 1861; 5 Envelopes. Measures approximately 3 1/2 x 6 x 1/8". 5 envelopes with engraved political cartoons. (Box 95, Folder 1)
    A political cartoon envelope set of five envelopes titled Championship Prize Envelope Lincoln and Davis in Five Rounds. Each envelope is unused and measures approximately 3 1/4" x 5 7/8". The entire face of each is taken up by an elaborately engraved political cartoon of a boxing match between Lincoln and Davis, chronicling the fight between the two leaders with the final envelope showing Lincoln wearing the championship belt and standing triumphant over a grease spot on the ground representing the vanquished Davis.
  - Come Back Here You Black Rascal... [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/4 x 5 1/2 (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Cotton [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 2 3/4 x 5 1/8" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - It's No Use a Knocking at the Door [carte-de-visite], 1865; Measures approximately 2 5/8 x 4". Carte-de-visite illustration of George McClellan and James Gordon Bennett. Pencil writing on verso. (Box 95, Folder 1)
    Carte-de-visite illustration of George McClellan and James Gordon Bennett, with bags in hand, knocking at the White House door in 1865.
  - J.D. His Marque. A.L. His Marks [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 2 3/4 x 5 1/8" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Jefferson Davis [Set of 14 cartes-de-visite], circa 1865; Measures approximately 2 3/8 x 4 1/4 x 1/2". 14 small cartes-des-visites approximately the same size, with images adhered to the paper. Smallest is 2 1/4" x 4", largest is 2 3/8" x 4 1/4". (Box 95, Folder 1)
    Some cards include photographer information on verso.
  - Jefferson Davis parody(?) [2 cartes-de-visite], circa 1865; Measures approximately 2 1/4 x 3 3/4". Two small cartes-des-visites featuring red and blue printed ink humorous illustrations possibly depicting Jefferson Davis. Pencil notations on verso of both cards. (Box 95, Folder 1)
    One card features a man with a rifle running toward Jefferson Davis(?) who shouts "Let me alo-o-o-ne" while a man nearby holds a pig by the tail and says "Yes, we will in a..." Other card depicts a bull with horns down about to ram Jefferson Davis(?). Behind the bull is the word "North" as the bull says "Come and take a Horn, Jeff." Davis responds "You go away and let me alone."
  - Lyndon B. Johnson, Lyndon Baines Johnson Library and Museum [postcard], 1983; 1 Postcard. Measures approximately 4 1/8 x 6". Political cartoon of LBJ by Blaine of the Hamilton, Ontario Spectator, marking the dedication of the Library-Museum on May 22, 1971. Card is postmarked August 27, 1983 at the library-museum. (Box 95, Folder 1)
    Political cartoon of LBJ sitting atop the library-museum bearing his name. LBJ is wearing a cowboy hat and boots and seems to be smiling and satisfied. The caption reads: D'yuh all mind if ah rest on muh laurels? Artwork by Blaine of the Hamilton, Ontario Spectator, marking the dedication of the Library-Museum on May 22, 1971. Card is postmarked August 27, 1983 at the library-museum. An 8-cent LBJ stamp is affixed along with two other stamps totalling 13 cents postage. It is noted as #448 of limited edition of 970.
  - Oh! Let Me alone! Jeff Davis Coat of "Alms" [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/8 x 5 1/2" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Secession Web. [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/8 x 5 1/2" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Southern Menagerie is Coming [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/8 x 5 1/2" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - The Country's in danger!--that's what's the matter. [envelope], circa 1861; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/8 x 5 1/2" (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - The Washington-Bryan Combination Picture: Shall the People Rule? [envelope], 1908; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 3 1/2 x 5 1/2". Illustrated fold-out envelope comparing President George Washington with 1908 presidential candidate William Jennings Bryan. Card is used (addressed, stamped and postmarked). (Box 95, Folder 1)
    Illustrated fold-out envelope comparing President George Washington with 1908 presidential candidate William Jennings Bryan. Card is used (addressed, stamped and postmarked).
  - [5 Sets of David Levine prints from The New York Review of Books], 1964-1970; 45 Prints. 5 folders containing multiple prints and indexes. (Box 95, Folder 10)
    Each set of prints contains about a dozen drawings of world leaders, artists, writers, and famous figures. 1 set from 1964, 2 sets from 1965 (slightly different contents), and 2 sets from 1970.
  - A Locofoco Before and After the Late Election: Hurra for Cass! / What! Old Zack Elected! [cartoon envelope and photographic reproduction], 1848; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 6 x 8". Original metamorphosis envelope is affixed with tape to backing. Reproduction is in photo corners on backing. Hand-colored cartoon envelope with pull tab that changes caption text, text on wine goblet and facial expression of the figure depicted. Includes photographic reproduction. (Box 95, Folder 2)
    Metamorphosis envelope showing two candidates for the 1848 U.S. presidential race, Zachary Taylor and Lewis Cass.
  - Farewell to Reagan [Set of 15 postcards], 1988; 15 Postcards. Measures approximately 4 3/4 x 6 1/2 x 1/4". Set of postcards in presentation envelope. (Box 95, Folder 2)
  - Martin Van Buren / William Henry Harrison [cartoon envelope and photographic reproduction], 1840; 1 Envelope. Measures approximately 4 1/4 x 5 3/4". Hand-colored cartoon metamorphosis envelope with pull tab that changes caption text, text on wine goblet and facial expression of the figure depicted. Includes photographic reproduction in photo corners attached to backing. (Box 95, Folder 2)
    Metamorphosis envelope showing two candidates for the 1840 U.S. presidential race, William Henry Harrison and Martin Van Buren.
  - Son of Reaganstein [Set of 15 postcards], 1989; 15 Postcards. Measures approximately 4 3/4 x 6 1/2 x 1/4". Set of postcards in presentation envelope. (Box 95, Folder 2)
  - How Columbia receives McClellan's Salutation from the Chicago Platform., 1864; 1 newspaper clipping. Single 1/2 sheet page, possibly clipped from magazine (Box 95, Folder 3)
    At the 1864 Democratic National Convention in Chicago, George McClellan was nominated for president and George Pendleton as nominee for vice president.
  - Union Generals. Department of the Mississippi., circa 1861; 1 Photo engraving. Significant foxing on paper. (Box 95, Folder 4)
    Mathew Brady is considered to be one of the earliest American photographers and the first American war photographer. Brady opened his photography studio in New York in 1844 and photographed Abraham Lincoln, John Qunicy Adams and Andrew Jackson, among other public figures.
    Attributed to photographer Mathew Brady and engraver John Rogers. Photographic depictions of six Union generals with an eagle at top. Includes Jeff C. Davis, not same person as Confederate President Jefferson Davis. Other photographs include: O.O. Howard, L.H. Rousseau, B.H. Grierson, and H.W. Slocum.
  - Soliciting a Vote [copy 1], 1852; 1 Lithograph (Box 95, Folder 5)
    Soliciting the vote of the working man by candidates competing in the 1852 presidential election.
  - Soliciting a Vote [copy 2], 1852; 1 Lithograph (Box 95, Folder 5)
  - The Sad Parting Between Two Old Friends, 1851; 1 Lithograph. 3 copies. Copy 1: Some minor foxing, discoloration at edges. Copy 2: Some pencil markings in upper right corner. Does not compromise illustration. Copy 3: Hand colored. (Box 95, Folder 5)
    Depicts Senators Benton, Foote and Calhoun in the "Shop of the Senate". Political cartoon regarding Benton's opposition to the Missouri Compromise of 1850 and the loss of Benton's senate seat in 1851 due to this stance.
  - Where's My Thunder?, circa 1850; 1 Lithograph. Two copies (Box 95, Folder 5)
    In regards to the Fugitive Slave Act of 1850.
  - [Amy cartoon by Jack Tippit, published February 20, 1985.], 1985 February 20; 1 Print. Original cartoon art, ink on paper. Art appears to be drawn in pre-produced panel which includes title and artist name. Printed, adhered caption and copyright notices added after/on top of drawing. (Box 95, Folder 6)
    Syndicated "Amy" cartoon original artwork published in newspapers February 20, 1985.
  - [Untitled John Branch editorial cartoon, published in San Antonio Express-News in 1989.], 1989 November 30; 1 Print. Original cartoon art, ink on paper. (Box 95, Folder 6)
    Editorial cartoon with no title or caption. Depicts the Capitol Dome as a telephone with the handset off the hook; it is surrounded by written "while you were out (of it)" phone messages regarding calls about the deficit, the Clean Air Bill, child care and campaign finance reform.
  - Night of the Long Knives, 1973; 1 Print. Original cartoon art, ink on paper. Includes blue drafting pencil and white-out or another type of error correction paint. Includes adhered, pre-printed text with copyright information. (Box 95, Folder 6)
    Original editorial cartoon artwork created for the Orlando Sentinel newspaper includes editorial layout notations. Political commentary on the federal budget cuts including NASA and public services.
  - [Set of 9 Collectors Prints from the Cartoon Art Museum, San Francisco], 1985-1995; 8 Prints. 2 copies of Prints No. 4 by Chuck Jones. (Box 95, Folder 7)
    Black and white reproduction prints of previously published syndicated cartoonists. Printed on thick paper with red border noting Cartoon Art Museum - Collectors Print No. Includes various contemporary artists: Will Eisner (Print No. 3), Chuck Jones/Warner Bros. (Print No. 4), Gahan Wilson (Print No. 5), Bill Watterson (Print No. 6), Lynn Johnston (Print No. 7), Mike Peters (Print No. 8), Pat Oliphant (Print No. 9), Harvey Kurtzman (Print No. 10).
  - [Collection of 33 cartoon prints from various artists], circa 2003-2005; 33 Prints. 33 digital prints on paper. (Box 95, Folder 8)
    Cartoons related to California politics and the 2003 gubernatorial recall, Hurricane Katrina, environmental issues, the oil industry, President George W. Bush, the United States, Iraq, Iran, and international politics. Possibly donation gift from the Cartoon Art Museum (SF).
  - [Set of 16 cartoon panel prints by Alden Erikson], circa 1991; 16 prints on paper. 1 print is signed and numbered 212/250, in pencil. (Box 95, Folder 9)
    Single panel humor cartoons commenting on politics, media and society.
- 5. International Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, 1690-2010; Series 5; 21.9 linear feet (13 boxes, 1 map folder)
  Contains approximately 593 drawings, prints, engravings, etchings, lithographs, broadsides, and ephemeral items. The earliest prints found in the collection are two German prints (circa 1690) by unknown creators: Don Miguel Zorrero Tuerto Cavellero de las Trencadas and Thro excedenz herr Oswald von Stroblbardt Injuriarum Licentiatus Other rare, early prints include Hogarth's works: Judith an Oratorio of Sacred Drama (circa 1732), the series A Harlot's Progress (1733), Datur vacuum (1736), and The Bench (1758). Contains several rare prints depicting King George III, early America, and the American Revolution: Farmer G--e Studying the Wind & Weather (1771), The Yankee Doodles Intrenchments Near Boston (1776), The Tea Tax Tempest (circa 1781) and A picturesque view of the state of the nation (1778). Other notable items include: two Chinese political cartoon prints by an unknown artist (circa 1975) and two S.C. Milter prints from India (1894). The collection is particularly strong in the number of James Gillray etchings published from 1782-1809, the majority of which were printed in London by publisher Hannah Humphrey.
  The ephemeral group includes calendars, cigarette cards, playing cards, trading cards, photographic prints, postage stamps, and postcards. Notable materials include War Cartoons No. 1-140 (1917-1918), a set of World War I era Black Cat cigarette cards illustrated by Louis Raemaekers, and an envelope of unpublished photographic prints documenting events in Tiananmen Square (circa May-June 1989) by an unknown photographer.
  - Emperors of Ancient China (Original Paintings by Palace Artists), circa 1990; Set of playing cards in paper box within a plastic box. (Box 111, Folder 21)
  - Mao Zedong, circa 1990; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 18)
  - Romanov, circa 1990; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 17)
  - Eichborns Politiker-Skat, circa 1990; Set of playing cards in plastic box. (Box 111, Folder 22)
  - The Economist 2011: An Illustrated Look at the Year Ahead, 2010; Staple bound wall calendar in original plastic wrap. (Box 124, Folder 7)
  - [L'oroscopo del neutro. Andro, non Andro...], circa 1940 (Box 124, Folder 1)
    Color postcard. Possibly depicts Charles de Gaulle.
  - [La passeggiata attraverso i suoi campi preferiti], circa 1945 (Box 124, Folder 1)
  - Noticiero Deportivo No. 2, circa 1955; 1 Print (Box 124, Folder 6)
  - [Greek postcard showing cherubs holding a note and a banner with Greek text over flames], circa 1974 (Box 124, Folder 1)
    Color postcard from Cyprus features three cherubs flying over a flame-covered terrain, holding a banner with text. One of the cherubs (likely depicting Henry Kissinger) appears to be older with bat wings instead of angel wings and is holding a sign that translates roughly to "Nobel Peace Prize." This card possibly depicts events surrounding the 1974 Turkish invasion of Cyprus.
  - [Vietnamese stamps], circa 1985 (Box 124, Folder 5, Item 1)
    15 postage stamps. Some used, with postmark.
  - [Groups of protesters in Tiananmen Square, China, May-June, 1989.], circa 1989 May-June (Box 124, Folder 6)
    Set of 13 color photographic prints featuring groups of protesters in Tiananmen Square, China. Many images of protestors, banners and signs, including cartoon images on signs. One image is of the Goddess of Democracy statue, May-June, 1989.
  - The (Australian) Prime Minister Series, circa 1996 (Box 124, Folder 3)
    Features drawings of prime ministers of Australia from 1901-1996 (Edmund Barton through Paul Keating). Each card has a black and white illustration of the prime minister, their dates of services, party affiliation and a memorable quote.
  - Concordia-Ball: 2 Februar 1931 (Grosses Raritäten-und Wachsfiguren-Kabinett), 1931 February 2; 1 Print. Small cloth-covered slipcase with string attached (perhaps for carrying or tying to secure book in slipcase), a book and ribbon bound card inside with a musical composition. Book cover has separated from binding. Pages very brittle. (Box 124, Folder 3)
    The Concordia Ball is an annual event hosted by the "Wiener Journalisten- und Schriftstellerverein Concordia" club (Concordia Association of Journalists and Writers in Vienna). The Concordia Ball was first held in Vienna, Austria in 1863. Source: Concordia Ball web site page for May 20, 2022 event - https://www.concordiaball.at/the-ball.html
    Possibly a party favor for the 1931 Concordia Ball in Vienna, Austria. Features caricatures of various politicians and celebrities including President Herbert Hoover, Marlene Dietrich, Albert Einstein, Sigmund Freud, Thomas Mann, Al Capone and others.
  - Invitation to The Political Cartoon of the Year Award (The Economist, The Political Cartoon Society), 2002 November 27 (Box 124, Folder 6)
  - [Anti-semitic postcards], circa 1935 (Box 124, Folder 1)
    4 anti-semitic and anti-communist postcards. Unused. Depicts 4 different scenes including Salome dancing with the head of John the Baptist and Stalin driving a carriage whipping at his workers.
  - Black Cat Cigarettes cards - Louis Raemaekers War Cartoons No. 1-140, 1917-1918 (Box 124, Folder 4)
    140 cigarette cards sleeved in plastic pages and banded together in 10 per page for a total of 14 pages. Versos of each card have identifying information about each illustration.
  - Louis Raemaekers World War I era - War Cartoons, 1916-1918 (Box 124, Folder 1-2)
    Louis Raemaekers is considered one of the most important editorial cartoonists of World War I.
    Approximately 90 different designs on 90 unused postcards.
  - Museo de la Caricatura, circa 2000; 1 Brochure (Box 124, Folder 6)
  - Exposition: "Anti-Nazi Cartoons" (The Work of Soviet Artists), circa 1942 (Box 126, Folder 1, Item 1)
    Loose set of about 40 black and white prints with cover/title sheet.
  - [12 Russian matchboxes in a paper box with Russian text and image of people holding red flags gathered in front of a domed state building or cathedral], circa 2000 (Box 130, Folder 1)
    12 Russian matchboxes (with matches) in a paper box.
  - Die Londoner Borse beim Eintreffen schlechter Nachrichten, 1922; 1 Print. Enclosed in mat and plastic. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    1922 reprint of 1780 anti-Semitism.
  - Der judische Geizhals, 1922; 1 Print. Enclosed in mat and plastic. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    1922 reprint of 17th century anti-Semitism.
  - Der wandernde Ewige Jude, 1922; 1 Print. Enclosed in mat and plastic. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    1922 reprint of 1852 anti-Semitism.
  - Psst...! Images par Forain Caran D'Ache..., 1922; 1 Print. Enclosed in mat and plastic. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    1922 reprint of 1898 anti-Semitic poster.